Guide to the Civil War Stereographs 1861-1865 PR 65-1
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Civil War Stereographs
1861-1865
PR 65-1
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
5.0 Linear feet (868 items, within Stereograph File)
The Civil War stereographs cover the entire period of the Civil War, from the first Battle of Bull Run through the surrender at Appomattox, and the triumphant parade of Union forces in Washington D.C. Most of the images were made in the Eastern Theatre, with scenes in Virginia by far in the majority.
Provenance
The Society acquired these items from various sources, although primarily from George T. Bagoe (1886?-1948) who specialized in collecting Civil War stereographs among other subjects. His collection came to N-YHS in 1960 and 1961. Other significant groups of views were acquired in 1922, 1923 and 1936.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Photographer Mathew Brady is represented, as well as his former employees Alexander Gardner, James Gibson, and Timothy O'Sullivan, who set up their own firm in 1863 because they wanted credit for their work which had previously all appeared under Brady's name. Other photographers include George N. Barnard, who photographed in Virginia and the Carolinas, Sam A. Cooley, who was the "Official Photographer" for the 10th Army Corps, and local photographers from Richmond, Gettysburg and other locations.
Scope and Content Note
The Civil War stereographs cover the entire period of the Civil War, from the first Battle of Bull Run through the surrender at Appomattox, and the triumphant parade of Union forces in Washington D.C. Most of the images were made in the Eastern Theatre, with scenes in Virginia by far in the majority. Views in northern states include naval shipyards in Massachusetts and Philadelphia, the battlefield at Gettysburg, and a rally and parades in New York City. Compelling images of death on the battlefield, and the destruction of cities, railroads and bridges show the devastating effects of the war. Individual and group portraits of participants are included along with images of soldiers relaxing in camps, drilling in the field, and ready for attack in trenches and other fortifications. There are images of African Americans fleeing slavery by crossing the Union lines, and of African Americans on southern plantations as well as serving in the Army and Navy. The damage to the Monitor after her fight with the Merrimac is shown, along with ships on the James River. Civilians also appear in the photographs, including photographers, artists and journalists, as well as a battlefield thief and members of the Sanitary Commission.
Most of the views presented here were published during the war by the photographers who made them, or by publishers such as E. & H.T. Anthony. Anthony's file was later obtained by General Ordway and published under successive imprints by John C. Taylor, and Taylor & Huntington to take advantage of the 25th anniversary of the war, and reunions that were held at the time.
Arrangement
Series #771-815 within Stereograph File.
Arranged geographically when know, otherwise arranged into series by subject. Series are further arranged by photographer or publisher's name.
Anderson Gallery, photographer; Barnard, George N., 1819-1902, photographer; Brady, Mathew B., 1823 (ca.)-1896, photographer; Confederate States of America. Army; Cooley, Sam A. (Samuel A.), photographer; E. & H.T. Anthony (Firm), publisher; Gardner, Alexander, 1821-1882, photographer; Gibson, James F., b. 1821, photographer; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1883--Portraits; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Portraits; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1865--Portraits; O'Sullivan, Timothy, 1840-1882, photographer; Roche, T. C., photographer; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Portraits; Soule, John P., photographer; Taylor & Huntington, publisher; United States of America. Army; United States Sanitary Commission.; Albumen prints; Armies--Officers; Confederate States of America; Georgia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; New York (State)-- History-- Civil War, 1861-1865; Parades; Portraits; Soldiers; South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Stereographs; Tennessee--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Afro-Americans; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Battlefields; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Casualties; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Destruction and pillage; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Military facilities; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Military life; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Transportation; United States--History--Civil war--Naval operations; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
- Series 771: Subjects--Civil War
  Scope and Contents note
  Civil War: painting of a battle; field telegraph station
  - 2 items, 1863 - [189-] (Box 71)
- Series 772: Subjects--Civil War--African Americans
  African Americans: "contrabands" in a Union camp; "contrabands", including men, women and children in front of a building; family in a wagon coming into Union lines
  - 3 items, 1863 - [188-] (Box 71)
- Series 773: Subjects--Civil War--Camp Life
  Civil War camp life: general views of camps, including tents, forts, rough buildings; men eating, reading relaxing, playing, washing, arrayed in formation, and with horses; includes African Americans; one view shows man with wife and child in camp
  - 43 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 71)
- Series 774: Subjects--Civil War—Dead
  Civil War dead: embalmer and corpse; unidentified Confederate casualty; grave of Union prisoners; members of a South Carolina regiment laid out for burial; an embalming building; African American soldier hanging from the gallows after his execution for attempted rape
  - 8 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 71)
- Series 775: Subjects--Civil War—Hospitals
  Hospitals: Frank L. Keyes, at home recuperating; Sanitary commission wagons and tents
  - 3 items, 1862 - 1865 (Box 71)
- Series 776: Subjects--Civil War—Navy
  Civil War, navy: ships, including monitor class ships, gunboats, rams and frigates; group portraits of sailors and officers on deck; includes both Confederate and Union ships
  - 33 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 777: Subjects--Civil War--Portraits, Civilians
  Portraits of civilians: Harper's Weekly artist; Godfor, a "battlefield vulture"; Jim Kerrigan, "The mollie squealer"; Major Pinkerton, and others, including Lincoln
  - 4 items, 1862 - 1866 (Box 72)
- Series 778: Subjects--Civil War--Portraits, Lincoln
  Portraits of Lincoln; studio portraits, and in camps, including a view of Gen. McClellan at Antietam; most are copy prints
  - 6 items, Before 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 779: Subjects--Civil War--Portraits, Officers
  Portraits of officers, including studio portraits and men shown in the field: Anderson, Bates, Butler, Corcoran, Crawford, Custer, Custer with Lt. J.B. Washington, a Confederate prisoner who was his classmate at West Point; Dix, Duryea, Farragut, Ferroro, Gordon, Grant, Hancock, Kearney, McClellan, Marcy, Moseby, Ord, Pleasonton, Patrick, Robertson, Rogers, Sherman, Smith, Strang, Sweeney, Thomas, Wheeler, Worden and others; some are Confederate officers; one view of Custer shows him with his dog.
  - 54 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 780: Subjects--Civil War--Portraits, Soldiers
  Portraits of soldiers: Duryea's Zouaves and other groups standing in formation; men in camp; John Burns, the hero of Gettysburg; man sitting on case of hard tack; orderly with horse; men in trenches; men in a sally port by a draw bridge; group at Mr. Foller's farm.
  - 11 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 781: Subjects--Civil War—Railroads
  Railroads: railroads that have been destroyed, including a railroad bridge; soldiers in front of a Baltimore and Ohio relay house
  - 4 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 782: Subjects--Civil War—Alabama
  Fort Morgan, Alabama, after Farragut's bombardment
  - 1 item, 1864 (Box 72)
- Series 783: Subjects--Civil War--Washington, D.C.
  Washington, D.C. and vicinity: Gen. McClellan's HQ; views on the Potomac; Grand Review of returning soldiers, showing men on parade, and the reviewing stand with dignitaries.
  - 12 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 784: Subjects--Civil War—Florida
  Florida: Signal tower near Jacksonville; Fort Marion, St. Augustine
  - 4 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 785: Subjects--Civil War—Georgia
  Georgia: Fort McAllister and Fort Pulaski, including interiors of the fort, artillery pieces, trenches
  - 9 items, 1862 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 786: Subjects--Civil War--Georgia, Atlanta
  Atlanta and vicinity: street views, railroad yards and depot; place where Gen. McPherson was killed; rebel fort north of the city; railroad outside the city that was torn up by Union forces; Potter house, damaged by Union fire; soldiers at picket station outside Atlanta
  - 19 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 72)
- Series 787: Subjects--Civil War—Maryland
  Maryland: soldiers seated above the Patapsco bridge outside Baltimore; ruins of Gen. M. Blair's home; crew of gun boat practicing; Sharpsburg: street, Lutheran church damaged by fire; pontoon bridge across the Potomac at Berlin, and ruins of bridge that it replaced
  - 8 items, 1861 - 1864 (Box 72)
- Series 788: Subjects--Civil War--Maryland, Antietam
  Battlefield at Antietam Maryland: dead lying in the field, and being buried; soldiers on the field, standing beneath trees; Tunker church; ruins of Mumma's house; Gen. Hooker's headquarters; Gen. Caldwell and staff; picnic party at Antietam bridge; Smith's barn, used as a hospital and straw huts nearby; signal tower on Elk Mt.; crowd gathered for Memorial Day at Antietam battlefield.
  - 48 items, 1862 (Box 72)
- Series 789: Subjects--Civil War—Mississippi
  The levee at Vicksburg, lined with steamboats
  - 1 item, 1864 (Box 73)
- Series 790: Subjects--Civil War--New York
  Parades on Broadway in New York, and barracks in City Hall Park.
  - 5 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 791: Subjects--Civil War--New York, Union Square Rally
  Great union Meeting, Union Square, New York April 20, 1861: crowds filling the park and surrounding streets, and lining the roofs of nearby buildings, with flags flying overhead.
  - 9 items, 1861 (Box 73)
- Series 792: Subjects--Civil War--North Carolina
  North Carolina: English Armstrong gun in Fort Fisher, N.C.
  - 1 item, 1861 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 793: Subjects--Civil War--Pennsylvania, Gettysburg
  Gettysburg: breastworks, fences, woods and the battlefield; dead on the battlefield; Confederate prisoners standing by breastwork; Round Top; Sugar Loaf Mountain; African Americans with a donkey: "all the livestock on Mr. Gill's plantation"; Lee's headquarters; Gen. Meade's headquarters; gate to the cemetery; John L. Burns' cottage; "Farmers' Inn and hotel, Emmittsburg, where our special artist was captured, July 5th, 1863"; home of James Gettys, founder of Gettysburg.
  - 60 items, 1863 (Box 73)
- Series 794: Subjects--Civil War--South Carolina
  South Carolina: forts, including Fort Walker on Port Royal, Fort Wagner, Fort Chatfield, Fort Marshall, Fort Putnam, and fortifications, possibly on Hilton Head showing interiors of the forts, soldiers on guard and with artillery; battery of "Quaker guns"; ordnance yard on Morris Island; Smith's plantation scenes, including group of slaves in front of slave quarters, preparing cotton for the gin.
  - 17 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 795: Subjects--Civil War--South Carolina, Beaufort
  Beaufort, S.C.: houses, some used as officers quarters, or military headquarters; streets; soldiers cemetery; 2nd U.S. Artillery, Colored with guns and tents; hospitals; boat landing; signal station, men on horseback below; store and post office; room decorated for ball; issuing stores to a group of "contrabands"
  - 25 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 796: Subjects--Civil War--South Carolina, Charleston
  Charleston: Confederate batteries in the city; destruction caused by the Union shelling; churches, markets, Institute Hall; commercial wharf and battery; Mills House; club house at the race course; tomb of J.C. Calhoun; O'connor House where Union officers were confined under fire.
  - 38 items, 1864 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 797: Subjects--Civil War--South Carolina, Fort Moultrie
  Fort Moultrie, Charleston Harbor, S.C.: view of interior of the fort, showing guns, the sallyport, cannonballs in stacks, looking out toward beach of Sullivan's Island
  - 8 items, 1861 - 1867 (Box 73)
- Series 798: Subjects--Civil War--South Carolina, Fort Sumter
  Fort Sumter: general view of the fort, and interior view in 1861, after Anderson evacuated; views of the fort after destruction and capture by Union forces, including the Union flag raising, April 14, 1865.
  - 44 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 73)
- Series 799: Subjects--Civil War—Tennessee
  Tennessee: views in Nashville; bridge over the Cumberland on the Louisville and Nashville R.R.; Knoxville R.R. depot at Chattanooga, group of rebel soldiers waiting transport north; Lookout Mountain; federal camp at Johnsonville.
  - 15 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 800: Subjects--Civil War—Virginia
  Virginia: camp and artillery of the Army of the Potomac; Fort Brady; Fort Corcoran; Falls Church; Cobb's Hill: the signal corps, and African American teamsters; Cold Harbor, including views of Gen. Grant and Gen. Rawlins; Gen. Butler's Headquarters; Fort Sedgwick; Fort Totten; Dutch Gap, including African American pickets on duty; Sulphur Springs, hotel, officers of the 60th New York Volunteers; graves of Union dead south of Wilderness church; Cumberland landing; Captain's mess, African American children waiting table; Bealton; the Rappahannock, during the battle of Chancellorsville; church in Centreville used as hospital; camp at Centreville; Quaker guns; fugitive slave crossing the Rappahannock; Culpepper; Warrenton, including view of the courthouse; Catlett's station; Aquia Creek landing; Lacy house, Falmouth; ruins of bridge at Germania Ford; 18th century carriage; Bethel Church; bridges on the Pamunkey; Savage Station.
  - 71 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 801: Subjects--Civil War—Virginia, Alexandria
  Alexandria, Virginia: bridge construction corps at work; interior of a barn; railroad yard, and slave pen; slave pen with soldier standing inside of it; Marshall house.
  - 9 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 802: Subjects--Civil War—Virginia, Appomattox
  Appomattox: pontoon bridge on the Appomattox River near Broadway Landing; house where General Lee signed the capitulation papers.
  - 5 items, 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 803: Subjects--Civil War—Virginia, Bull Run
  Bull Run: views on the battlefield at Bull Run including remains of the dead and graves, soldiers on horseback and Sudley's Ford and church, Robinson's House, ruins of houses, Beauregard's headquarters (later McDowell's), a monument, men lounging by tents at a picket's station; Sherman's battery on its return from Bull Run; bridge at Bull Run built by McDowell's engineers; T.H. O'Sullivan and photographers wagon; painting of the battle.
  - 17 items, 1861 - 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 804: Subjects--Civil War—Virginia, Cedar Mountain
  Cedar Mountain, Virginia: house, riddled with cannonballs; officers of the 10th Maine on the battlefield; dead horses; graves of Union soldiers; battery fording the Rappahannock; Culpepper courthouse, with group of Confederate prisoners.
  - 6 items, 1862 (Box 74)
- Series 805: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, City Point
  City Point, Virginia, on the James River, supply point and headquarters of Union forces during the siege of Petersburg: wharves, sailing ships, barges, steamboats, General Grant's headquarters, portraits of General Grant, one with his wife and son, orderly with Grant's horse Cincinnati, Gen. Rawlins, wife and child, soldiers and winter quarters, soldiers serving out rations, army wagon going to Commissary, graves of soldiers near the hospital
  - 32 items, 1864 - 1865 (Box 74)
- Series 806: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Fair Oaks
  Fair Oaks: frame house on battlefield used at a hospital; Professor Lowe observing the battle of Fair Oaks from his balloon; Gibson's battery of horse artillery; soldiers and artillery by frame house; redoubt on the front; soldiers in front of Quarles house; men and cannons at Fort Sumner, Fair Oaks
  - 14 items, 1862 (Box 74)
- Series 807: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Fortress Monroe
  Fort Monroe and vicinity: views of the fort, including fortifications and moat, a large artillery piece; group portraits of men in camp; tents in Camp Hamilton, bridge destroyed at Hampton, near Fortress Monroe; Zouaves at Camp Butler
  - 10 items, 1863 (Box 74)
- Series 808: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Fredericksburg
  Fredericksburg: general views of the town, looking across river, and from Tyler's battery; Philip's house on fire; dead in coffins, or covered with blankets, men, including African Americans, preparing to bury them; wagon train crossing the Rappahannock; men with crutches in yard of hospital
  - 9 items, 1863 (Box 74)
- Series 809: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, James River
  Views along the James River, Virginia: camps, including the construction corps camp at Belle Plain,; bridges, including pontoon bridges, destroyed Richmond and Petersburg R.R. bridge; Belle Plain landing and steamboats and other vessels; Aiken's landing a monitor class ship, and barges; signal tower; Dutch Gap and canal, including construction views, a view after the bank was blown out; water battery near Ft. Brady; Fort Brady; masked battery, fort Darling; obstructions in the river; sailing vessels at Westover landing; steamboat New York waiting for exchanged prisoners
  - 31 items, 1862 - 1865 (Box 75)
- Series 810: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, North Anna River
  North Anna River, Virginia: pontoon bridges; 50th N.Y.V. Engineers constructing road at Jericho mills on south bank; Jericho Mills at North Anna; Chesterfield bridge from rebel redoubt; line of breastworks occupied by Union troops on north bank; men bathing in river, railroad bridge in the distance
  - 14 items, 1863 - 1864 (Box 75)
- Series 811: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Petersburg
  Views in and around Petersburg: mortars at battery; redoubts and soldiers; buildings and houses, including interior view, damaged in bombardment; tobacco warehouses used by rebels as prison; rebel dead in the trenches; Chevaux de frise obstructions; breastworks and confederate dug-out quarters; Petersburg railroad bridge; trestle-work bridge on the southside railroad; dam on the Appomattox River near Petersburg; log church built by the Engineers, with Corps of Engineers symbol over door; bomb-proofs, including quarters and kitchen; rebel encampment with tents and log quarters; men in tent during the "dog days"; Fort Abbott, occupied during the siege by Lincoln
  - 72 items, 1864 - 1865 (Box 75)
- Series 812: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Richmond
  Richmond, Virginia: general views; Libby Prison; Jefferson Davis mansion; Gen. Lee's residence; ruins, including two views that viewed sequentially create a panorama of destruction of the city; 5th Pennsylvania Cavalry on battlefield; capture rebel guns; the Capitol; Richmond and Petersburg R.R. depot and locomotive; "Castle Thunder" prison; ruins of Danville railroad bridge; Drury's Bluff, near Richmond; First New York Battery cannons; grave of J.E.B. Stuart in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond
  - 38 items, 1860 - 1865 (Box 75)
- Series 813: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Spotsylvania
  Spotsylvania, Virginia: dead and wounded at Mrs. Allsop's, near the Spotsylvania courthouse, where the barn was used as a field hospital, and the dead were buried
  - 13 items, 1864 (Box 75)
- Series 814: Subjects--Civil War--Virginia, Yorktown
  Yorktown, Virginia: fort and landing at Yorktown, including cannons and mortars, ships; Camp Winfield Scott, including Gen. McClellan's tent; Confederate fortifications; group portrait of English officers
  - 22 items, 1862 (Box 75)
- Series 815: Subjects--Civil War--West Virginia
  Harpers Ferry, W.Va., during or directly after the Civil War: general views; ruins, including the railroad bridge; John Brown's "Fort"; "contraband" camp
  - 10 items, 1865 (Box 75)